Katan! Or
24th day of the Omer, last day of not only מדות, Middot,
but of all of קדשים, Kodshim, and day after יום ירושלים, Yom
Yerushalayim, so it's appropriate that we will be wrapping up the learning
here about the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash today. We start top of
ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, ל"ז עמוד א', Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph, פרק רביעי
משנה ג'. Perek Revii Mishnah Gimmel. So, we were dealing with the
gate into the היכל. Heikhal. We did for the big curtain on
the front of the אולם. Ulam. The אולם Ulam was an opening
that was 40 אמות Amot tall, which was basically, what did we
say, like 60 feet tall. And then that was the tallest, then
all the other openings in the מקדש Mikdash were 20 אמות, Amot,
30 feet. And the היכל Heikhal had basically two doors and it
was 10 אמות Amot wide and had two doors, five אמות Amot
each door on both front, two front doors and two back doors.
The two doors on the outside, two doors on the inside. Now
we are continuing to look inside of the היכל. Heikhal. So let's
take a look here. Whoops,
there was two doors that opened from the אולם Ulam into the
היכל. Heikhal. The width of the wall of the היכל Heikhal was
six אמות, Amot, like nine feet, it was a very thick wall.
So there were two doors in the front of the width of
the wall and then say back doors, you don't mean back doors.
No,
no, I don't mean back doors. I mean then you went through
the width of the wall and then two more doors, like double
doors, right, double doors. Okay, so now
where are we? ושלשים ושמנה תאים היו שם. Ushloshim ushmonah ta'im hayu
sham. There were 38 like cubbies, but actually we'll see they were
quite large. They were not just cubbies, little like, I don't know
what you would call them, closets, maybe closets would be a good
translation. But they were tall also as we'll see. חמשה עשר בצפון,
Chamishah asar batzafon, 15 on the north. חמשה עשר בדרום, Chamishah asar
badarom, 15 on the south. ושמנה במערב, Ushmonah bama'arav, and eight on
the west. So if you take a look, do you still have
that nice colored picture? Cubicle. Cubicle. Yeah, maybe a cubicle. That's true.
Okay, but it's more I think it's more like a closet. I'm
not exactly sure what it was used for. Anyway, if you take
a look, look here, you have 5, 5, and 3, but that's
not 15, 15, and 8. So we are about to see. Everybody
remember high school? I don't know what high school you went to,
I didn't go to a high school like this, but most people
did where you had like these lockers, you know, and you had
lockers on top of lockers. So essentially that's what we're going to
be dealing with. These are going to be like huge, almost walk-in
closets
on
five tripled, five tripled, and in the back three, three, we'll see
three, three, and two, eight, which makes for 38. Which makes for
38. So let's take a look.
Okay, so
I don't understand. How
do you get 15 and 15 is 30, then 3, 3, 3
is 9.
3, 3, and 2.
Oh, why is it two?
I have no idea. Okay, so who knows, they only needed 38.
Okay. חמשה
עשר, Chamishah asar, 15 in the north, 15 in the south, and
15 and 8 in the west. שבצפון ושבדרום, Shebatzafon v'shebadarom,
the ones in the north and in the south, חמשה על גבי
חמשה וחמשה על גביהם, Chamishah al gabi chamishah v'chamishah al gabeihem,
5, 5, and 5, three rows of 5. שבמערב, Shebama'arav, שלשה על
גבי שלשה ושנים על גביהם. Shloshah al gabi shloshah ushnayim al gabeihem.
3, 3, and 2. There you go, so that's 38. Now of
course, if they're that tall, because we're going to see how do
you get to the top ones? Right? Let... oh there you go,
that's a nice picture. So you see that? I mean there's major
like, yeah, they're not like closets, you know, they're like walk-in closets
is essentially what they are. Okay, finally.
Yeah so that's the amazing thing, thank you, is that we are
going to find out that in the היכל Heikhal they had like
more storage space, it's going to sound like I don't know more,
but anyway a ton of storage space. And then of course that
would seem like to be the least accessible of the spaces, right?
So in the עזרה Azarah here we talked about, you know, various
לשכות Lishkahot and so on, but we're going to see that there's
going to be a ton of storage space in the היכל Heikhal
and it never tells us what they were used for.
So Artscroll footnote says these cells were used for the storage of
gold, silver, and other valuable articles owned by the Temple and cites
a source called תבנית היכל. Tavnit Heikhal.
Okay, so somebody speculated that. But you know, but so what is
that? So they sort of, which is an interesting speculation, that it's
basically or every all the gifts that people gave
maybe just assuming that this is where they just stored like the
treasure house, because we always talk about the storage house, right? Remember
we learned about that in the previous right, מסכתות Masechtos about people
that donate and various and where does all that get stored.
So it's why you take the expensive items, put them in the
most holy place, it's elevating material wealth. There was plenty of space
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Right, I well I guess also because it's more of the most,
that's an interesting point. I assume also because it's the most protected
place. So if it's the most inner, it's the most protected. Right,
who was going to steal? Right. Who goes in there? But the
Babylonians, the Romans. Right, once they're in there, they can take it
anyway. And they were worried about the כהנים. Kohanim. Yeah, I don't
know. I don't know. It still reminds me about that story a
few months ago, right, when they found that temple, where was that?
In India, that had like a billion dollars of gold in it.
Yeah, people, various donations
that just kept on getting stored away.
In not a particularly wealthy area of India. Right.
So but it's not a bad speculation because we, I mean I
hear Rivka's question, but we have not heard about where the wealth
was stored that people donated.
It's true. You tend to feel like in a שול shul you
don't watch your bag so much. Right. You feel whoever is in
here is not going to steal. Right. So that's why it's odd
that they're using the most holy spaces for a very. That's what
it used to be doing a long time ago. Think about it.
That's elevating gold and silver.
I know, but I'm just saying maybe not because it was holy
and more that it was inaccessible is the only thing. This was
the one thing that was locked up that had all these.
Yeah, they were worried who was going to steal it.
Yeah, I hear. I don't know. Otherwise, otherwise we don't know what
it was used for.
I mean I understand, right.
It was more that was more ceremonial. Right. All right. I don't
know, but we don't know what it was used for. It doesn't
say.
ברטנורא Bartenura says some of these
were weaving the פרוכת. paroches.
There was another thing that was called בית הפרוכת. Beis HaParoches. So,
I don't know, a lot of this is speculation. Okay, let's keep
on going. ושלשה פתחים. V'shlosha pesachim. So now we had all these
rows, okay, and these were like I said, these were basically like
walk-in closets, they were huge spaces. We'll see in a minute exactly
how thick the wall was and how much space they had for
them. But anyway, ושלשה פתחים היו לכל אחד
ואחד. U'veshlosha pesachim hayu l'chol echad v'echad. Now here you had from
any one of these closets, we'll call it, you could get into
the other closets. They had three doors. אחד מהתא מימין ואחד מהתא
משמאל. Echad min hata m'yamin v'echad min hata m'smol.
When you were in the closet you could access the other closets
to the sides. It was like in hotels adjoining rooms. Okay, not
exactly clear why that was necessary to get to the sides. Why
don't you just walk out and you go to the other one?
But what was more necessary was the one that gets you on
top because maybe there was some type of a ladder or something,
like how do you get to the high ones? Right? I mean
the high ones are eight, ten, fifteen feet up. Maybe you get
to it from going through a trapdoor in the bottom. But you'd
still need some type of steps or something, some type of a
ladder.
תפארת ישראל Tiferes Yisrael says
there was a spiral staircase.
Okay, spiral
staircase. Okay, fine. ואחד לתא שגביו. V'echad l'ta she'gabav. So one going
to the to the sort of closet above, to the space above.
ובקרן מזרחית צפונית, U'v'keren mizrachis tzfonia,
now obviously on the rooms on the, well let's take a look,
you know, here the rooms at the very northeast and southeast, you
wouldn't need a door to, well we'll see whether you need a
door to the side because there was no side closet on those.
So it says like this: ובקרן מזרחית צפונית U'v'keren mizrachis tzfonia in
the northeast room, that would be, that would be here, right, the
northeast room. So there's nothing to this side. There's some here, there's
some above. By the way, and obviously on the rooms on top
you didn't have a door above, right, obviously. So anyway, but the
normal ones would have ones to the side and above. So in
the northeast room,
you know what this reminds me of? My Dungeons and Dragons days,
you know, and then there's a trap door and then you go
underneath. Anyway, okay. ובקרן מזרחית צפונית U'v'keren mizrachis tzfonia in the northeast
room היו חמשה פתחים. hayu chamisha pesachim. There were five doors. אחד
התא מימין, Echad hata m'yamin, one to the
right, ואחד לתא שגביו, V'echad l'ta she'gabav, one above, ואחד, v'echad, now
you don't have a room on the side, a normal one of
these closet rooms, but what you have
is, ואחד למסיבה, v'echad l'mesiba, one for the walk-around. We're going to
talk about what the walk-around is in a minute. ואחד לפשפש, v'echad
l'pishpash, one for the sort of the crawl space, ואחד להיכל, v'echad
l'heichal, one to the היכל. heichal. So what does that mean? So
the one to the היכל heichal is here. Just go straight into
the היכל heichal like this. Okay. The one into the crawl space,
remember we said that when they had to open the door to
the היכל heichal they went through a little crawl space or whatever
it was here, a tunnel here, then into the היכל heichal and
they opened the door from the inside. Right, when they opened it
in the morning. So it was through this room that they did
that. There was a crawl space through the wall of the היכל
heichal into this room. From this room into the היכל. heichal. I
don't know or whatever it is, a tunnel. Okay. A tunnel into
this room, then a tunnel from this room into the היכל heichal
and then they would open the door. So this is how they
would get to the door to open it in the morning. That's
two. Three, into the side. Okay. Four, above. And five, to the
מסיבה, mesiba, the walk-around, which we'll get to in a minute. But
by the way, talking about why you needed side doors, right, if
you look at this picture, right, notice that. Here it added as
a special door, one into the היכל Heichal. *heichal*, which suggests that
all of the other תאים te’im, *ta'im*, all of the other closets
did not have a direct door into the היכל Heichal. *heichal*. So
how'd you get into them? Right? If none of them had a
door into the היכל Heichal. *heichal*, so it seems like the only
way to get into them, and this is why they needed side
doors, was through this first היכל Heichal *heichal* that had an access.
That remember that door, that was always closed. Okay, that was God's,
that was always closed. So the only way, let me finish, the
only way to get in, because it didn't mention any of the
others had doors into the היכל Heichal, *heichal* and here it added
it as a door, would be to get into a door into
the first one in the northeast corner and from there you had
to move all the way around to get to any others and
go up and whatever. So if they were really storing stuff in
there, that would be pretty you know inconvenient. You know, you'd have
to leave like a passageway by where the doors are, you're minimizing
your storage space.
It's not as convenient as Amazon would provide.
Yeah, exactly. Does not seem to be the most efficient. But maybe
from this end you can
get into it from היכל Heichal. *heichal*.
Oh, maybe, that could be, maybe from that way. Good question whether
that door was also closed. Okay, now we're gonna talk about
we'll keep on talking about this structure. Let's take a look. ד'
התחתונה חמש ורובד שישה *dalet hatachtonah chamesh verovad
shishah*. Now
these different closets basically because they're because you have to stand on
the higher on the one above. Now you would have imagined, I
would have imagined they would just carve it into the stone and
therefore the stone would have been like a nice you know slab
in the middle which serves as a roof for one and a
floor to the next. But apparently it sounds like the way they
cut it is they cut out the whole thing and then they
put like a wood floor, some type of beams between each one.
Well if you're gonna put beams between each one, you need to
support the beams. So the way they supported the beams was that
if this is the היכל Heichal *heichal*, right, this is the closet
space being built, so anyway if if
if the closet here, you see the picture, the closets are not
built right right up against it. There's like a wall, a thick
wall, right, so if here's the closet, here's the היכל Heichal, *heichal*,
so the first level you're gonna have to have the wall a
little thinner so that they can put the beams down here. You
see? And then you're able to build up that level because you
have to put the beams. And then when you get to the
next level, the wall's gonna have to be even also inset a
little bit more, right, this thickness of the wall's gonna have to
be cut in so then you can put the beams down at
that level, which means that the size of the closets progressively grows
as you go up. Okay, you got a picture there. Okay. So
התחתונה חמש *hatachtonah chamesh*, so the bottom room was five אמות amot
*amot*, ורובד שישה *verovad shishah*, and it had like a row, a
roof of six אמות amot *amot*. Those were like the beams on
top. Therefore והאמצעית *veha'emtza'it*, the middle room which was built on the
roof of the bottom one, שישה *shishah*, ורובד שבעה *verovad shivah*, and
a row of seven above it, והעליונה שבעה *veha'elyonah shivah*, and the
top room had a floor of seven אמות amot *amot*. שנאמר היציע
התחתונה *shene'emar hayatzia hatachtonah*,
the bottom room חמש באמה רוחב *chamesh ba'amah rochav*, מלכים *Melachim*, in
the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. We keep on quoting
פסוקים *psukim*. The only פסוקים *psukim* we have is from the first
and the third. So we keep on quoting פסוקים *psukim* from the
first and the third and applying it to the second. Okay. והיציע
התחתונה חמש באמה רוחב והתיכונה שש באמה רוחב והשלישית שבע באמה רוחב
*vehayatzia hatachtonah chamesh ba'amah rochav vehatichonah shesh ba'amah rochav vehashlishit sheva ba'amah
rochav*. Okay, so was five, six and seven was the width. Now
what was this walk-around, the מסיבה mesibah, *mesibah* that the northeast one
opened into? והמסיבה היתה עולה מקרן *vehamesibah hayetah olah mikeren*. Now this
was really again I call these things crawl spaces, maybe you could
walk in them, but this really was going to be the like
you know like sort of you know like in buildings you have
like the ventilation duct thing, you know whatever. So you have a
way to get you know sort of it goes through the floors
and gets all the rooms. This is how do you get to
the top of the of the היכל Heichal *heichal*, to the roof.
And this is a crawl space that basically goes through over in
the ceiling area over all of these closets, over all of these
rooms, and eventually opens up into a into stairs onto the roof.
So it's on an incline? You get to stairs, you climb into
it through stairs and then you go and then you go through
this type of a of a walk space or crawl space. So
let's take a look. It said there's a tunnel into the מסיבה
*mesibah*, that this one had... No, this said no, not a tunnel,
an opening, like a roof opening into the מסיבה *mesibah*. So you
had a roof opening here straight up, which was going into the
top room and then you had an opening let's say at this
angle over here that got me into that crawl space that's going
to get... I'm missing something. I thought this one had a this
bottom one had a had an opening into this מסיבה *mesibah*. It
did. Okay, and this מסיבה *mesibah* got you to the roof. Oh,
you're right. So the מסיבה *mesibah* had to be on an incline
because you're starting you mean at the lower level and you have
to eventually get up. That's correct. Except I don't know how much
you walked first to get into the מסיבה *mesibah*, how much of
the incline was to get to the מסיבה *mesibah*, how much the
incline was the מסיבה *mesibah*. Okay, so מסיבה היתה עולה *mesibah hayetah
olah*. So מסיבה *mesibah* was going up. this מסבה *Mesiba*, this whatever
walkaround, would go up מכאן *mikan*, so I guess Michael's right because
the phrase היתה עולה *haita ola* makes it sound also that it
was at an incline. Also the picture has like little lines which
I assume types of stairs or something indicating that it would that
you'd be walking up it. Okay, היתה עולה מכאן מזרחית צפונית *haita
ola mikan mizrachit tsfonit* from the northeast לקרן צפונית מערבית *l'keren tsfonit
maaravit*, it would get you to the back, the northwest, ובה היו
עולים לגגות התאים *uvah hayu olim l'gagot hata'im* and from this they
could get to the tops of the תאים te’im, *ta'im* of these
of these closets, of these spaces. היה עולה במסבה *haya oleh bamesiba*
so somehow this מסבה *Mesiba* could give you access, you know, to
the top space of the closets, I don't know why you'd want
to be on top of the closets but maybe to get from
the top down into them or something. And not only so it's
going sort of, you know, it's going at the top level. היה
עולה במסבה ופניו למערב *haya oleh bamesiba ufanav l'maarav*, so you'd be
going up on it, right, so it's clear it's an incline, you're
right, the text says going up, facing west because you're now moving
to the back of the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*. הלך על כל פני
הצפון *halach al kol pney hatzafon*, you go the whole north עד
שהוא מגיע למערב *ad shehu megia l'maarav*, you get to the furthest
west, the northwest corner. הגיע למערב *higia l'maarav*, you got there, והפך
פניו לדרום *vehafach panav l'darom*, then you make a 90-degree turn facing
south. הלך כל פני המערב *halach kol pney hamaarav*, you go the
entire west wall עד שהוא מגיע לדרום *ad shehu megia l'darom* to
come to the southwest. הגיע כלפי דרום *higia klapei darom*, got to
the southwest, והיו פניו למזרח *vehayu panav l'mizrach*, you made a 90-degree
turn to the east. היה מהלך בדרום *haya mahalich badarom*, so now
you went the whole south עד שהוא מגיע לפתחה של עליה *ad
shehu megia l'pitchah shel aliyah* until you got
to the opening to the roof.
Okay, so basically this thing you would walk, right, without an incline,
you'd get into here, from you'd have to go up, you go
down here for, it doesn't show
it this way, but
you'd be going here because it gets higher up in, you know,
in the building, you know, keep on going up and up in
the sort of height of the building. The building is 20 אמה
amah, *amah*, 30 feet, so you know, you're starting from down here
from about a, you know, 8-10 feet high, you're going up as
you're going to the back, this way, this way, and from here,
it's a big walkaround to get there, you're going to go up
into the roof. Okay. Now, by the way, it's not just that
this is 20 אמה amah *amah*, we're going to see in a
minute, this 20 אמה amah. *amah* the lower section, this entire היכל
Heichal *Heichal* had a second story.
So in order to get to the roof, you had to go
up 40 אמה amah, *amah*, 60 feet. All right, so that could
explain why you needed to go
all this distance, it's a very long roundabout way, but if you
need to get up 60 feet, you want to do a lot
of gradual climbing, okay? Does that clear? Meaning the entire height of
the, of the היכל Heichal, *Heichal* is 60 feet. You're starting here
and you're slowly going up like stairs all three directions till finally
you're at the top and you're going to go get access to
the roof. Why did they have it on this side? Correct. There
was only one access to the roof. Here it is again, gives
you a sense about how big it is, right? So if you're
starting down here, you know, somewhere near person height and you have
to get all the way to the roof, there's a lot of
stairs you have to climb all the way till you get to
the top of the roof. So it goes all the way around
till it gets you to the top of the roof. What do
they do in the roof? We'll see. Okay. First of all, you
might want to clean it from all of the bird droppings. That
must have been one of the tallest buildings in the world at
the time.
Really? Yeah. Wow. How big is the Taj Mahal? That's huge, right?
But that was built 1,500 years after Herod's. Wow. What's 1,500 years?
Nothing's as tall, the pyramids in Egypt were the tallest buildings
in the world
until about a century ago. But they're not on a mountain. This
is on a mountain, right? So it would have been very elevated.
Yeah. How big was those? About 500 feet high. Okay, so this
was only, what did we say?
60 feet. This was only 60 feet. Yeah.
60 אמה amah *amah*. No, 40 אמה amah. *amah*. It's starting on
flat. Right. It's 40 אמה amah. *amah* high. 60 feet. All right,
so all right, so now we're getting up to
40 אמה amah *amah*, so we did this whole walkaround in through
this walk space, right, which is going up and up and up.
Okay, now you get to the access to the roof. הגיע לפתחה
של עליה *higia l'pitchah shel aliyah* where are we? שפתחה של עליה
פתוח כלפי הדרום *shepitchah shel aliyah patuach klapei hadarom*. It is opening,
it opens towards the south, which basically means it's in the south
because you went all the way around like this and now you're
at the south, so in the southeast corner, right, you went this
whole walkaround, now you're at the tip in the southeast corner and
you're going to access, so it's still going higher, right? Right, you
keep on going, you're right, you keep on going higher and higher
and higher, you're absolutely correct, it keeps on saying about going up.
You have to go up 40 אמה amah *amah*. Okay, so now
you're right at the top of the, near the roof and you
have access to the roof. I don't know if it would pass
fire code, but okay. All right, anyway, שפתחה של עליה פתוח כלפי
דרום *shepitchah shel aliyah patuach klapei darom* ובפתחה של עליה היו שתי
כלונסאות של ארז *uv'pitchah shel aliyah hayu shetei klunsaot shel erez*. Now,
it wasn't there either that it was just straight at the top,
there were these two poles of of cedarwood שבהן היו עולים לגגה
של עליה *shebahen hayu olim l'gagah shel aliyah* that through them you
would get to the top. Now how would you So it's basically
describing a ladder. Okay, so anyway, so you had access to this
now to the roof. Okay, לגגה של עליה, ובראשן פספסין מביא בעליה
בין הקודש לבין קודש הקודשים. u-veroshan paspasin mavia ba-aliyah bein ha-kodesh l'vein
kodesh ha-kodashim. So again, it probably should be בראשי פספסין, berashei paspasin,
which is phrased before. There was some division, you're on the roof,
right? You want to respect the space that's over the קודש קדשים.
kodesh kodashim. How do you know the space that's over the קודש
קדשים kodesh kodashim when you're on the roof? So there were these
פספסין paspasin which again either means like little little like you know
bolts of wood coming out indicating where the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim
which was opposite the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. I mean, you'd have
a sense when you were getting very far to the back, but
if you wanted to know exactly where it began. Or, but and
again, Albeck says פספסין paspasin means that there was some mosaic there
that indicated a line of mosaic that indicated the line between the
קודש kodesh and קודש הקדשים. kodesh ha-kodashim. Okay. But if you're on
the roof and you need to do something on the roof, it
doesn't really make... I know, but you want to sort of show
respect. I mean, it's true, it doesn't exactly have the קדושה kedusha
of קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, but right. הלולין, ha-lulin, and this is
a famous section of the משנה mishna that's often quoted, היו פתוחין
בעליה לבית קדשי הקדשים. hayu petuchin ba-aliyah l'veit kodshei ha-kodashim. There were
basically like openings, holes, but they would lower down like a dumbwaiter
on the roof that you would lower down people in... they must
have had some type of a gear system or whatever, you know,
that they would lower people into the קודש הקדשים kodesh ha-kodashim to
do work on the קודש הקדשים. kodesh ha-kodashim. Yeah, that sounds for
pulleys, right. What? That sounds for... I'm sorry. That's described elsewhere. Yes,
yes, פסחים pesachim and it's right. והלולין היו פתוחין בעליה. ve-ha-lulin hayu
petuchin ba-aliyah. So there were like little holes, openings in the roof
לבית קדשי הקדשים l'veit kodshei ha-kodashim that would be opposite the קודש
הקדשים. kodesh ha-kodashim. שבהן היו משלשלין את האומנין בתיבות. shebahen hayu meshalshelin
et ha-umanin be-teivot. They would lower down the craftspeople in these boxes,
right, on some type of pulley system. It's a long way to
go. It's like... that's also you talk about the biggest building, how
about the first elevator? Right. Although didn't they find in... what was
it? What was that city that was preserved in by the volcano?
Pompeii. Pompeii. Didn't they find that they were able to... what was
it? Get like... did they have an elevator system or they were
able to get heated piped water like multiple stories high or something?
They had the technology that they didn't have for like hundreds and
hundreds of years, thousands of years later, anyway. Piped water. Okay, anyway,
בתיבות, be-teivot, כדי שלא יזונו עיניהם מבית קדשי הקדשים. kedei shelo yazunu
eineihem mi-veit kodshei ha-kodashim. So they should not literally their eyes should
not יזונו yazunu which is a word like... I'm trying to think
of a good word. Yeah, but it's a sexual word. It's like
fornicate. It's like to derive this illicit pleasure from the קודש קדשים.
kodesh kodashim. What? Feast your eyes. Yeah, but meaning right. I mean,
it's the whole idea. Obviously there's always often these marriage metaphors used.
Is it from מזון? mazon? Oh, I thought it was from זנות.
znut. Feast... sate themselves. Really? That is interesting. I always thought it
was from זנות znut because the whole idea was that there's this
intimacy between God and כל ישראל kol yisrael and the כהן גדול
kohen gadol and there's this whole marriage metaphors. And here they are
sort of, you know, interlopers as it were. I wonder what Joe,
what is your English... Joe, what does your English say? The Soncino
says... It doesn't have? No, they do. Feast... piece... Feast on the
beauty of the Holy of Holies. Feast their eyes. So they do
have it as מזון. mazon. They have it as מזון. mazon. Interesting.
Okay. All right. There you go. I wonder if anybody says the
way I said it, but okay. I stand corrected. Anyway, so they
had a little picture here of this. Right. So I was going
to say, so I was going to say how does it prevent
them? Well, that's interesting because what does it prevent... how does it
prevent them? This is seeing whatever else they don't need to see.
Well, right. That has as a pretty big box. That has as
a pretty big box. I understood that the box was much narrower,
you know, so that it's like they have blinders on. Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. Although although that gives them a lot of space. I guess
you need space to move around, but then you can easily, you
know, see stuff peripherally. I imagine tight because of the sense that
it would be protected within them. Right, right. Right? Not just blinders,
you would feel protected. Right. So anyway, yeah, it certainly would make
it... it certainly would make them, you know, keep it clear to
them that they had to be focused and not just look around.
They weren't there for a tour. Okay. So, why did they go
on the roof? Maybe the only reason they went on the roof
was to go down to the קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, which is
a big thing to get to the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. So
it also makes you appreciate like, you know, it's also a good
preparation, like don't treat this lightly. You know, that I imagine as
well. Could be a leak in one of the... I understand. Right.
You could go up to fix the leak in the roof or
to clean the roof or whatever. But I'm also saying the fact
that you had to go through this huge high climb to get
to the roof and then to go to the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kedashim is also a good way to impress upon the workers, you
know, to not to treat this lightly. Okay, so now משנה ו.
Mishnah Vav. והיכל מאה על מאה על רום מאה. VeHaHeichal meah al
meah al rom meah. Now והיכל VeHaHeichal was—does he do טבילה tevilah
or anything like that in order to, you know, work there? If
you go in that way, I don't think so because it's not
the normal דרך ביאה. derech biah. The, the idea of וריחוץ ידיים
ורגליים verichutz yadayim veraglayim is only when you're נכנס nichnas through the
normal דרך ביאה. derech biah. You need טבילה tevilah to get in
here? Yeah, but וריחוץ ידיים ורגליים, verichutz yadayim veraglayim, you had to
be טהור, tahor, but וריחוץ ידיים ורגליים verichutz yadayim veraglayim was particularly
when you did עבודה avodah on the מזבח mizbeach or when you
entered into the היכל. Heichal. So but whether you needed ריחוץ ידיים
ורגליים, richutz yadayim veraglayim, you might not even have to be a
כהן Kohen to go in there if you're a craftsman, you know.
תוספות, Tosafot, המאירי, HaMeiri, רמב"ם Rambam state that a לוי Levi or
a ישראל Yisrael could be נכנס. nichnas. Yeah, so you don't, but
it wasn't normal, it didn't have the normal requirements of going in
because you had to be a כהן Kohen and ריחוץ ידיים ורגליים
richutz yadayim veraglayim because you were going in from the top. It
wasn't considered a normal כניסה knisah to the היכל. Heichal But he
had to get into this מסיבה, which means you had to get
somewhere through the היכל. Heichal Ah, that's an interesting point. Oh, you
entered it through the אולם Ulam anyway. That's an interesting point. How
could you go in? Well, if you didn't go in the היכל
Heichal, proper, if you went through those doors, then you probably, it's
never considered a כניסה knisah to the היכל, Heichal. but that's a
good point. Okay, so now והיכל, VeHaHeichal, we're finishing this today. והיכל
מאה על מאה על רום מאה. VeHaHeichal meah al meah al rom
meah. So והיכל, VeHaHeichal, which does not mean just the inner space,
but it means the entire structure was a hundred by a hundred
by a hundred high. Now, the hundred, one direction we're counting is
the length of the אולם, Ulam, which extended beyond most of the
היכל. Heichal, So it's a hundred here, if you count this, a
hundred to the back and a hundred high. Okay, I actually said,
I actually underestimated. I said 60 feet, 40 אמה, amah actually I
underestimated. I wasn't, so I wasn't joking back then. Yeah, I underestimated.
It was really right, right. I forgot because as we're going to
see, a lot of middle layers. Okay, so technically yes, if it's
100 אמות amos high, that's what, 150 feet. So you got a
lot of climbing. 150 feet in total? Well, let's read it. No,
no, because there's like multiple levels. Let's read it. Okay, והיכל מאה
על מאה על רום מאה. VeHaHeichal meah al meah al rom meah.
האוטם, Ha’otem, which is basically the foundation, שש אמות. shesh amot. וגובה
ארבעים אמה. Vegovah arbaim amah. And then you had 40 אמה ama
high. So actually, I'm sorry, I had misstated it. It was not,
right, because the door for the היכל heichal? was 20, but the
actual height of the היכל, heichal right, was the same, I'm sorry,
so I had misstated it, it was 40 אמה. ama Okay, so
the first layer of the היכל heichal where you have the three
rows of these whatever, right, was 40 אמה, ama 60 feet. Okay,
so they weren't just narrow crawl space and short crawl space. Right,
so you take basically, right, so you had, you had a שש
אמה shesh amah base, you got 40 אמה ama which was the
first, right, which is 60 feet, okay, the first sort of story
of the היכל. heichal. So for each of these you had these,
these תאים, te’im, right? So you're talking about what, you could have
almost 20 feet, 15 feet, right, even with some space between them
for one of these, you know, you'd have to have at least
10 אמות amos for one of these תאים, you know, big, big
תאים, right? And this is the first layer here. And that's where
you got to the roof. And then when you would gain access
from the very down here, you would access this and this would
get you all the way up to the roof. But we're only
at the first level. It's going to get to be 100 אמה.
ama Okay, so right, I actually had mistakenly said 20, it was
40. Okay, so now, okay, so 40 אמה. ama ואמת כיור. Ve’amat
kiyur. Now there's an אמה ama? of כיור. kiyur. כיור Kiyur is,
anybody know what the word כיור kiyur means? I had to look
it up. כיור Kiyur is a sink. כיור, Kiyur, let me say,
is actually molding, engraving, that they would do at the top of,
you do like sort of, you know, at the top of the,
right, before you get to the roof. What does ArtScroll say? Decoration.
Decoration, thank you. Okay, molding, right, crown molding. It's spelled differently than
the כיור kiyur of the wash basin. It's spelled the same way,
but it's an 'u' not an 'o'. כיור Kiyur not כיור. Kiyor.
Okay, now, ואמהתיים בית דלפה. Ve’amataiyim beit dilfah. There was two אמות
amos, of בית דלפה, beit dilfah, which means, which most explain, the
רמב"ם Rambam explains differently, most explain mean basically it's like some type
of beams that you would put before you would lay the, the
roof, you know, which would also be the floor of the next
story, you'd have, you'd have beams going, cross-beams before you lay actually
the planks. ואמה תקרה, Ve’amah tikrah, an אמה amah for the roof.
ואמה מעזיבה, Ve’amah ma’azivah, and then another אמה amah for the plaster.
Okay, so that gets you so how much was that? It was
molding which was one, and then there was two of these cross-beams,
right and then there was the actual laying of the roof which
was another and then the plaster which was another so that's four
so now we're 44 and six for the base we're now 50
אמות amos. high. Okay, lots of builds. I mean, it was a
lot of work. That's true. Well, Herod used, I think, slave labor.
Yeah, as did שלמה המלך. Shlomo Hamelech. There you go. Well, that
was, it depends if it was tax or slave. Right, doesn't sound
like it was slave, that sounds more like it was tribute, but
I don't know if there was a big difference. Okay, anyway, so
what does this בית צלופה beis tzelofa exactly? It's like you see
when they like if you were to take off these things, right?
You'd see these like steel girders, right? So some type of like
girders before you lay the actual roof and the plaster on top.
It's surprising building Herod's Temple took a long time to build. Right.
Yep. Okay. Now. Okay, וביסא uveisa now, where did I skip something?
וביסא ואמת תקרה ואמת מעזיבה וגובה של עליה מ"ם אמה. uveisa v'ama
tikra v'ama maziva v'govah shel aliya mem ama. Now you had, we
were wondering what did you use all of these like closets and
rooms for? Well guess what? They had an entire second story that
we have no idea what was stored there. Okay, you had on
top of this entire thing which was 40 אמות amos high and
then with all of the foundation and the roof 50 אמות, amos.
you had another 40 אמה amah high, 60 foot high second story
built on top of it. Was it a dormitory for the... I
don't think so. It was for the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. I
don't think so. I think we would have known if it was
a dormitory. It was for the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Oh, okay,
for some kiddush. וגובה של עליה מ"ם אמה. v'govah shel aliya mem
ama. So now this whole second story was another 40 אמות. amos.
אמת כיור, amat kiyur, an אמה amah, of molding, אמתים בית צלופה,
amatayim beis tzelofa, two אמות amos. of, you know again, these girders,
אמת תקרה ואמת מעזיבה. amat tikra v'amat maziva. So again you have
the roof and then the plaster. So where are you now? You're
three, four, five. No, אמת כיור amat kiyur one, two, תקרה מעזיבה
tikra maziva five. You're five. I think I miscounted. There was five.
So anyway, okay, so you were 51 and now you had 40
plus five for all the roofing. So now you're 51 and 45,
you're 96. Now we've got the roof. How are you going to
get to 100? Okay. וג' אמות מעקה. v'gimel amos ma'akeh. You needed
a, you had a מעקה. ma'akeh. You had a what do you
call it? A... Right, exactly, a fence. Although you probably weren't really
obligated because it wasn't a בית דירה. beis dirah. But if you're
going to have workers going up you're going to want a fence.
ואמה, v'ama, so that's okay, 99. ואמה כלה עורב. v'ama kala oreiv.
And an אמה amah. for the thing to destroy the ravens, to
chase away the ravens. Scarecrow. So they basically had like pointed metal
sticks to prevent the ravens from coming. You know, you got burning
sacrifices and you got a big building, the ravens are going to
want to hover, so you had basically these pointy things to keep
the ravens away. רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, לא היה כלה
עורב עולה מן המדה. lo haya kala oreiv oleh min hamiddah. No,
you can't count that as part of the 100, that wasn't part
of the structure itself. אלא ד' אמות היה מעקה. ela dalet amos
haya ma'akeh. Okay, it was a four אמה amah fence. All right,
anyway you had 100. So this was huge. Right? And again, go
back to this idea... I mistakenly gave you half the size. The
inner size here was 40 אמה amah even the level you went
into, 60 feet high. So having three layers of these, you know,
rooms on each side was no big deal for something that's 40
אמה ammah 60 feet high. And obviously there's a lot of climbing
to get from close to the bottom all the way to the
top of the roof which was this walk around. But again, what
did they use all the rooms for? What did they use the
entire second story for? Right? No idea. All right. Wait, so when
we said to get to the roof that was when you were
jumping up up to 100 אמה? Yeah. Yeah. You have a lot
of climbing. I'm trying to understand, so you had this 40, then
you climbed up the ladder... No, first you got to the 40
from presumably the bottom one, then you have to get to the
top of the 100. Right, but I thought it described what you
do to get to the 40. Then it says this whole thing
was on top of it all over. No, before it wasn't telling
you. No, before it just said you went through this walk around
to get to the top of the roof and we're understanding that
meant a lot of climbing. I was just wondering about the utilitarian
purpose. It sounds like it was built for grandeur. Right, so there
was no particular purpose for it, so maybe eventually somebody used it
but maybe it wasn't built for... But then wouldn't you want it
to be just without the second story, you walk in and you
see something super tall? That's what we're accustomed to if you go
to a cathedral or something you see these huge high ceilings, so
maybe that wasn't the style. Maybe it was to impress from the
outside. After all, how many people came in? Right, right, well that's
true. The ספרי Sifrei claims that the היכל heichal. actually does require
a מעקה maaka but the אולם Ulam does not. Why not? That's
a good question. I'll have to look. You know, it's not a
בית דירה beis dirah certainly. Okay, anyway, let's keep on going. Okay,
ממזרח למערב מאה אמה. Mimizrach lema'arav meah amah. Now that was the
height, 100 אמות. amos. From east to west, 100 אמות. amos Let's
take a look. כותל האולם חמש, Kotel ha-Ulam chamesh, so the wall
of the אולם Ulam was five אמות. amot Yeah, it was very
thick walls. Remember we said that they had to crawl through this
wall to get to the היכל, Heichal. so five אמות. amot, והאולם
אחת עשרה, ve-ha-Ulam achas esreh, the אולם Ulam was 11, just like
11 was the right, עזרת ישראל, Ezras Yisroel, עזרת כהנים, Ezras Kohanim,
so 11 was also the width of the אולם. Ulam. So now
we're up to 16. כותל ההיכל שש, Kotel ha-Heichal shesh, then six
of the wall to the היכל. Heichal So that is... what are
we up to? 16, 22, right? And that six אמות amot. was
what you crawled through to get into the היכל and then to
walk through whatever to get into the היכל to open up the
door. So now we're up to 22. בתוכו ארבעים, Besojo arbaim, 40
אמה on the inside, which includes the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, so
we're 62, right? 62. אמה טרקסין. Amah traksin. Now, I'm sorry, no,
it does not include the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. 40 you get
to the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, so we're 62. אמה טרקסין, Amah
traksin, טרקסין traksin was just referred to the space which had the
wall between the קודש Kodesh and קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, but in
the second בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash? because it was so high, they
couldn't make a thin wall an אמה wide and that high, so
they had two curtains so that you could walk, you know, between
one and then the other. One was a little bit removed from
one wall, the other removed from the other. That was called טרקסין.
traksin. So was there an אמה space between them? There was an
אמה, yes, from the outer edge of one curtain to the outer
of the other was an אמה. It doesn't seem like you can
really fit through between the two. Well, they're thin curtains, that gives
you almost an אמה between them. And they're describing the קודש קודשים
Kodesh Kodashim with what was in it? Right. Well they didn't describe
what was in the היכל, this is all describing the structure and
not the content. It is, I guess, it's true. You're right. I
mean it is true, they did describe... They did describe the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. They did, right. They did describe the מזבח mizbe'ach and what's
out in the yard. They did not really describe... yeah, they did
not really describe what's in the היכל. Yeah, yeah, it's a good
point. I mean there are other גמרות Gemaros that describe it, but
in the משניות Mishnayos like a detailed description like this, you know,
I don't think so. It's a good point. I don't know. Maybe
if the reports they got was from the כהנים, Kohanim, how many
כהנים Kohanim actually... although כהנים Kohanim would have seen inside here because
they would go in for the קטורת ketores and for the מנורה.
Menorah. It's a good point. Good questions. All right, so now we're
up to 63. ועשרים אמה בית קודש הקודשים. Ve-esrim amah Beis Kodesh
Ha-kodashim. קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim was 20, that's 83. כותל היכל שש,
Kotel Heichal shesh, six now to the back. That's 89 of the
thickness of the wall. Now we start getting into these rooms. והתא
שש, Ve-ha-ta shesh, the room was six. We said it was five,
six, and seven, but we're measuring sort of the medium-sized room, so
that's another six. What are we up to? Anybody keep score? 95.
והכותל התא חמש, Ve-hakotel hata chamesh, and then five for the back
wall, and there you go. So you had these thick walls in
between these closet or these room spaces and you got to 100.
Now מצפון לדרום שבעים אמה, Mitzofon ledarom shivim amah, from the north
to the south 70 without counting the אולם, Ulam, which we'll get
to because we said it was 100 by 100. כותל המסיבה חמש,
Kotel hamesibah chamesh, so the wall, if you start looking here at
the north, the wall before you get to the walk space to
get to the roof was five. והמסיבה שלוש, Ve-hamesibah shalosh, the walk
space was three, is eight. כותל התא חמש, Kotel hata chamesh, then
the space till you get to the to these rooms was five.
So that's 13. והתא שש, Ve-ha-ta shesh, the average-sized room is six,
19. כותל היכל שש, Kotel Heichal shesh, then six the wall to
the היכל, 25. בתוכו עשרים אמה, Besojo esrim amah, 20 אמה width.
What are we up to? 25 and 20, 45. Now and then
it's going to be another obviously 25 on the other side. You
can sort of see that, right? 25, 20, 25. So we're going
to get to 70. כותל היכל שש, Kotel Heichal shesh, then six,
והתא שש, ve-ha-ta shesh, וכותל התא חמש, ve-kotel hata chamesh, five. Now
instead of opposite here in the middle of the wall, instead of
having the walk around... now you did have to walk around at
this wall too, because you had to be getting up top. Okay,
but that was let's say higher. This was presumably at a lower
level, right? That was way up there. So down at a lower
level what was going on in this space? It was בית הורדת
המים, Beis horadas hamayim, the place where the water is spilled out.
They would use this for... trying to remember... let's finish it and
then I'll check. שלוש אמות, Shalosh amos, three, וכותל חמש אמות, ve-kotel
chamesh amos, and then five, and that gets you 70. האולם עודף
עליו חמש עשרה אמה מן הצפון. Ha-ulam odef alav chamesh esreh amah
min hatzafon. וחמש עשרה אמה מן הדרום. vechamesh esreh ama min hadarom.
The אולם Ulam extended beyond the seventy, fifteen אמות at each end.
So you see the way right the אולם Ulam looked, right? It
extended beyond, right? And that was fifteen אמות, gets you a hundred.
והוא נקרא בית החליפות. vehu nikra beit hachalifot. The space where it
extended beyond in this space here was called בית החליפות. Beit HaChalifot.
Why was it called בית החליפות? Beit HaChalifot? ששם גונזים את הסכין.
shesham gonzin et hasakin. There they hid the knives. Interesting. So first
of all, why is it called בית החליפות? Beit HaChalifot? So because
חלף... chalaf... Yeah, so I was thinking right now, the word for
a knife is a חלף. chalaf. That’s a יידיש Yiddish word, right?
A יידיש Yiddish word. So I don’t know, so people try to
say maybe חליפות chalifot means קרבן, korban, there’s a פסוק pasuk in
תנ"ך Tanach that חליף chalif could mean a קרבן. korban. Not exactly
clear how this means knife, but this was called, this was where
they hid the knives. Interesting that it says גונזים, gonzim, hid them.
Who were they hiding them from? Like you know, I hide my
knives from my kids. I don’t know why they'd hide the knives.
And it's also funny, you know, you'd think exactly you'd want this
stuff out in the עזרה, azara, to be putting this type of
stuff in the אולם. Ulam. I mean, it seems very funny. Maybe
they were גונז-ing gonzeh the knife when they nicked and broke, and
they, you know, and they were גונז-ing gonzeh it because it was
כלי המקדש klei hamikdash that they had to do גניזה, genizah, but
why only the knives? Maybe the knives were the things that were
the easiest, you know, that broke the easiest, right? I mean, they're
the most delicate of everything. Let me just kind of remember, like
you know, when they open the, in relation to the תמיד, tamid,
did they open the היכל? What? In relation to the תמיד. tamid.
They had to open the היכל before they שחטו shechted the תמיד
tamid because it has to be פתח פתוח. petach patuach. Right, is
there anything more about someone retrieving the knife to give to the
כהן? kohen? Right, it says they got all of the כלי המקדש
klei hamikdash out of whatever, out of the room. It did not
speak about getting knives. Right, so it could be גונזים gonzin means
it required גניזה genizah if it actually broke. Okay, so these weren't
actually used knives, right? What? Right, the people. Oh. I don't know,
it's not clear. It's not clear, well he says when they were
in use. Yeah, he says חלף chalaf is a Latin or לשון
רומי. Lashon Romi. Really? Meaning a knife? Yeah. Interesting. Oh wow, tell
all the שוחטים shochtim that when they say חלף chalaf they're actually
using a Roman or Latin term. Right, is there a difference between
the words hide and store? I mean they actually say hide. Yeah,
גונזים, gonzin, I know, גניזה, genizah, I think גונזים gonzim primarily means,
it does primarily mean like when it can no longer be used,
like not to be stored. So store would be if it's going
to be used, but they say hiding. Right, גונזים, gonzin, right, simple
גניזה genizah means putting away because it can't be used. But here
it's saying the walls of each of the chambers of knives contained
twenty-four recesses in which the members of the משמרות mishmarot stored their
שחיטה shechita knives. They said stored. Store, but you know, גניזה genizah
means maybe then when it was their turn maybe they took them
out and put them somewhere. I understand. It's interesting that they would
do it in the אולם. Ulam. Who do they quote who says
that? רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi in יומא? Yoma? רש"י Rashi in יומא,
Yoma, okay. And then they also say the chambers were called בית
החליפות Beit HaChalifot because the word חליפות chalifot means knives and in
the book עזרא מחלפים תשעה ועשרים. Ezra machalafim tisha ve'esrim. Yeah, that
should be, yeah. What? מחלפים תשעה ועשרים, machalafim tisha ve'esrim, twenty-nine swords.
Right, right, I mentioned that in עזרא. Ezra. Or they say in
Arabic the word is salkaji, or solbarji. Anyway, for a knife that's
used for killing, it would be again surprising that it would be
in the אולם, Ulam, yeah, in such a holy place. So you
can't even have... Alright, I'm going to have to call an end
to this discussion because we have fifteen minutes to finish the מסכת.
masechet. Alright, so וההיכל, vehaheichal, no more talking. וההיכל צר מאחוריו ורחב
מלפניו, vehaheichal tzar me'achorav verachav milfanav, the היכל was narrow at the
back and wide at the front. Obviously you can see that, that's
the whole point that it extended in the front. ודומה לארי, vedomeh
le'ari, similar to a lion. שנאמר הוי אריאל. shene'emar hoy Ariel. Yesterday
we said the אריאל Ariel was the word for the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
So in יחזקאל Yechezkel it's a word for the מזבח, mizbe'ach, in
ישעיהו Yeshayahu it's a word for the entire היכל. Okay, so ארי
ari is a lion. אריאל קרית חנה דוד. Ariel kiryat chanah David.
מה ארי צר מאחוריו ורחב מלפניו. mah ari tzar me'achorav verachav milfanav.
I guess it's because of the like the face and the mane
of the lion, right? It looks bigger in the front. So אף
היכל צר מאחוריו ורחב מלפניו. af heichal tzar me'achorav verachav milfanav. To
make it look like a lion. הדרן עלך Hadran alach the fourth
of היכל. And now the last פרק perek of the last מסכת
masechet of קדשים. Kodshim. כל העזרה היתה אורך מאה ושמונים ושבע על
רוחב מאה ושלושים וחמש. Kol ha'azarah hayetah orech me'ah ushmonim vesheva al
rochav me'ah ushloshim vechamesh. It was one hundred and eighty-seven by one
hundred and thirty-five. ממזרח למערב, Mimmizrach lema'arav, from the east to the
west, one hundred and eighty-seven. קפ"ז. Kof-peh-zayin. מקום דריסת רגלי ישראל אחת
עשרה אמה, Makom drisat raglei Yisrael achat esreh ama, so where the
ישראל Yisrael went was eleven אמות. מקום דריסת הכהנים אחת עשרה אמה,
Makom drisat hakohanim achat esreh ama, where the כהנים kohanim went before
the מזבח mizbe'ach was eleven. Again the ישראל Yisrael could go there
if they needed to, if they were צורך עבודה. tzorech avodah. המזבח
שלושים ושתיים, Hamizbe'ach shloshim ushtayim, right, the מזבח mizbe'ach we said was
thirty-two by thirty-two, so we're twenty-two and thirty-two is fifty-four. בין אולם
למזבח עשרים ושתיים, Bein ulam lamizbeach esrim v'shtayim, 22 in this space
between, which might have been all taken up by the stairs at
least whatever. Anyway, 52 we have 22, 32, we were 54, 22
we are 76. Where were we? Been 22, 76. שלשים ושתיים בין
אולם למזבח עשרים ושתיים. Shloshim v'shtayim bein ulam lamizbeach esrim v'shtayim. אמה
החיל, Ammah hacheil, ק' אמה. Kuf ammah. Not simply החיל, hacheil, what
is it? היכל. היכל ק' אמה. Heichal kuf ammah. So we had
just said that this whole thing was a hundred, so we're up
to what? 176? Yes? Okay. ק' אמה Kuf ammah ואחת עשרה אמה
לאחורי בית הכפורת v'achat esrei ammah l'achorei beit hakapporet and 11 אמה
from the back of היכל to the outer wall. So that is
187. Interestingly, by the way, when we were counting the אולם Ulam
as 100 by 100, we were doing it from the outside dimensions,
right? Including the thickness of the wall. Here we're doing the inside
dimensions, okay? So it's 187 till you get to the back wall.
This is a hundred here. This is a hundred here. No, we're
not counting עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. From this wall, from עזרת ישראל,
Ezrat Yisrael, this is 187. From the inside of עזרת ישראל Ezrat
Yisrael to the back wall, that's 187. So the space in, the
space in the middle of the gateway wall would not be considered
part of the עזרה? Azarah? Well, that's actually a question about whether
the space inside had the קדושת עזרה kedushat Azarah or not, and
the גמרא Gemara says that it depends whether the door, it really
was an ambivalent space. So if the door of these rooms were
opened into the עזרה, Azarah, then it's defined as part of the
עזרה Azarah and had קדושת עזרה. kedushat Azarah. If they were opened
out, and if they were both, then they split the difference. Okay.
But and the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, by the way, as you
can see, is a perfect square, so that was 135 by 135.
Okay, but now we're doing the width. 135 here of the עזרה.
Azarah. מן הצפון לדרום מאה ושלשים וחמשה, Min hatzafon ladarom meah ushloshim
vachamishah, 135. מן הכבש ולמזבח ששים ושנים. Min hakeves v'lamizbeach shishim v'shnayim.
From the כבש, ramp, interestingly, we're not starting with the space between
the כבש, ramp, we'll get back to that. From the כבש ramp
to the מזבח mizbeach was 62. Now, if you remembered, we said
actually the מזבח mizbeach was 32 and the כבש ramp was, anybody
remember? 32? 32. 32 plus 32 is not 62, it's 64. So
there's a little bit of a question. Some say that the basic
answer given, yes? The top of, but the top is only 28.
Well, right, exactly. So some say, well first of all there's an
interesting mathematical error רמב"ם Rambam makes because רמב"ם Rambam actually says that
when he said 32 it meant that the incline was 32, but
of course as and the base is only 30. So that's why
the incline is 32 and the base is only 30. That can't
be the problem, right? He lived after Pythagoras. What? He lived after
Pythagoras. Yeah, so that was a little curious. Anyway, the רמב"ם Rambam
certainly knew his math. Anyway, the explanation is, is that here on
the base it is, here on the base it is 30, okay,
that's what רמב"ם Rambam meant too, but right, the מזבח mizbeach as
it ever kept on going in like this, so if you measure,
if you measure the sort of from here to here where the
כבש ramp starts, stops, it's going to go... it'll be 32, yeah.
But at the base it's really only 30, okay. So anyway, so
that's how you get 62. 62. מן המזבח ולטבעות שמנה אמות Min
hamizbeach v'lataba'ot shmoneh amot from the מזבח mizbeach to the טבעות rings
where they did the קרבנות korbanot and בית המטבחיים beit mitbachayim was
eight. So we're up to 70. מקום הטבעות עשרים וארבע, Makom hataba'ot
esrim v'arba, the space for the טבעות rings was 24, we're up
to 94. מן הטבעות לשלחנות ארבע, Min hataba'ot lashulchanot arba, so from
them to the שלחנות tables is four, is 98. מן השלחנות לננסים
Min hashulchanot lannanasim from the שלחנות tables to the ננסים platforms is
ארבע, arba, is four, we're up to 102. There's a little problem,
which is it didn't speak about how much space the שלחנות tables
took up. So people say okay, between those four and four, somewhere
the שלחנות tables were in the middle, but it's interesting it didn't
mention it. Some have an interesting suggestion that the שלחנות tables were
portable and they moved them around as needed, so it didn't mention
the space of the שלחנות. tables. Very moveable tables. Yeah, I know,
very portable, exactly. There are actually three different maps here. Okay, so
we're up to 98. מן הננסים לכתל Min hananasim lakotel from the,
from the little stands to the wall, we're also not measuring the
space of the ננסים. nanasim. So some of the stuff here isn't,
isn't included in these measurements but not being measured. עזרה שמנה אמות,
Azarah shmoneh amot, so we're up to what are we up to?
106? I lost count. I think we're up to a little bit
more. Anyway, והמותר v'hamotar whatever we didn't measure here that was the
difference between that and 135, בין הכבש לכתל bein hakeves lakotel was
the space between the כבש ramp and the wall, right, because we
started with the כבש, ramp, we didn't, we didn't start with where
right the gap between the כבש ramp and the wall. ומקום הננסים,
Umokom hananasim, oh no, here it does mention and of course the
space taken up by the actual, by the actual what do you
call it? Pillars, right, platforms. So anyway, so and of course what
we also didn't measure, so we skipped over the room the space
for the שלחנות, shulchanot, we don't know the exact... Some of that
exact thing. Okay. Moving on. That's 135 by 135. שש לשכות היו
בעזרה. Shesh lishkot hayu ba'azarah. Now there were six לשכות. lishkot. Now
if you've been with us since תמיד, Tamid, you know what? Six
לשכות lishkot we were talking about five gates and seven gates and
thirteen gates and all these gates opened into a לשכה, lishkah, right?
לשכת הקרבן Lishkat HaKorban and לשכת ה... Lishkat Ha... this and לשכת
ה... Lishkat Ha... that. So for some reason it's mentioning other לשכות
lishkot that we've not mentioned before. And if you look at your
picture, all the לשכות lishkot we're going to mention now are the
ones sort of like right at the beginning. So all the לשכות
lishkot we had mentioned before were with the gate or sort of
from the place of like from the אולם Ulam to the מזבח
Mizbeach or from the מזבח Mizbeach backwards. The לשכות lishkot we're mentioning
now are in the space of עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and עזרת
כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. Okay, so you see that? Before we had mentioned
all the rooms in the עזרה, azarah, they were these backwards. Now
we're mentioning the rooms that are opposite the עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim
and עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. So, שש לשכות היו בעזרה. Shesh lishkot
hayu ba'azarah. It's funny, in the עזרה, azarah, you know. שלש בצפון
ושלש בדרום, Shalosh batzafon v'shalosh badorom, three in the north, three in
the south. שבצפון לשכת המלח, Shebatzafon Lishkat HaMelach, the room of salt
where you can probably guess what they did there, they kept all
the salt for the קרבנות. korbanot. By the way, there's a whole
question here, there's a whole question of גרסאות girsaot whether we're talking
about the north ones or the south ones. People have it reversed,
which is which. Okay, this picture has that we're talking about the
south ones. I know, but I'm saying north and south, there are
different גרסאות girsaot which is which here. Anyway, so our גרסא girsa
says that we're talking about the north, but our picture has that
we're talking about the south. Okay. Anyway, לשכת המלח, Lishkat HaMelach, the
room of the salt. לשכת הפרוה, Lishkat HaParvah, the פרוה Parvah room.
The question what פרוה Parvah means, could be a name of the
person, but this was the room where the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
on the top of it did his טבילות tvillot on יום כפור
Yom Kippur and so that was at least what was done on
the roof. Not exactly clear what was done in the room itself.
לשכת המדיחים Lishkat HaMadichim and the room for rinsing, you might remember
is rinsing out the, right, the stomach of the קרבנות. korbanot. They
did that in a particular room, not outside, because it was particularly
disgusting. Okay. So, לשכת המלח שם היו נותנים מלח לקרבן. Lishkat HaMelach
sham hayu notnim melach l'korban. Okay, there they would put salt for
the קרבן. korban. Not they put the salt on the קרבן, korban,
put the salt for the קרבן. korban. לשכת הפרוה, Lishkat HaParvah, what
would they do? שם היו מולחים עורות. Sham hayu molchim orot. So,
whatever, I don't know where my head is. I said a second
ago whatever, fine, it doesn't matter. It says explicitly here what they
would do with it. So there they would actually put salt on
the skins, because you needed to preserve the skins and work the
skins, right? The כהנים kohanim got the skins, you didn't want them
to spoil, so you would salt them after the קרבן korban was
flayed to preserve them for the כהנים. kohanim. Isn't that צורך עבודה
tzorech avodah so they shouldn't be allowed to do that in the
בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash. I was thinking exactly the same thing. You
know, I don't know. I mean it certainly was... What? They stored
salt which was given value. No, I understand that, but why would
they take it out? Let them use their own salt and let
them do it outside of the בית המקדש. Well, I don't know
who paid for the salt or if they used מקדש Mikdash money
for the salt, but... It's only in the עזרה. azarah. There's also...
there's also... Well, if it's בקדושת עזרה b'kedushat azarah is as a
קרבן. korban. והפרוה V'HaParvah is a מקוה mikva in there. Well, the
roof of it would be... the roof would be the מקוה. mikva.
That was the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כפור. Yom Kippur.
That's the next line. Yeah, it's a good question. All right, you
people ask questions I don't have answers to. Where were we? ועל
גגה היה בית טבילה לכהן גדול ביום הכפורים. V'al gagah hayah beit
tvillah l'Kohen Gadol b'Yom HaKippurim. On the roof was a place where
they would go to the מקוה mikvah for the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. לשכת המדיחים ששם היו מדיחים קרבי
קדשי קדשים ומשם מסבה עולה לגג בית הפרוה. Lishkat HaMadichim shesham hayu
madichim kirvei kadshei kodashim umisham mesibah olah l'gag beit haParvah. So there
they would rinse out the, you know, the innards of the קרבנות
korbanot to get all the fecal matter out and there they would
also have access to the roof of the בית הפרוה, Beit HaParvah,
so the כהן kohen would go from there to get to the
roof. Interesting place to have him go through that room. Maybe it
would be a room other people wouldn't want to go in. Here's
this about פרוה. Parvah. הברטנורא HaBartenura says that אדם מכשף ששמו פרוה
בנה אותה לשכה על ידי מכשפות. Adam mechashef sheshmo Parvah banah otah
lishkah al yedei mechashefut. Lovely. The רמב"ם Rambam says it's from the
word פרים parim because they would use it to salt out the...
exactly, the פרה parah or skins of the שור. shor. Okay. Moving
on. שבבדרום... Shebadarom... הברטנורא... HaBartenura... he gets it from the רמב"ם. Rambam.
The רמב"ם Rambam says differently: שאין איש המגושי שחתר בקיר העזרה בלשכה
זו כדי לראות את העבודה והרגוהו על כן נקראת הלשכה על שמו.
She'ein ish haMagushi shechatar b'kir ha'azarah balishkah zu k'dei lirot et ha'avodah
v'haraguhu al ken nikret halishkah al shemo. I don't know where they're
bringing it from, but not exactly... well the רמב"ם Rambam wouldn't say
he built it out of witchcraft, that's what I'm saying, the witchcraft.
Okay, anyway, moving on. שבבדרום, Shebadarom, okay, we have like three minutes,
people. לשכת העץ, Lishkat HaEtz, לשכת הגולה, Lishkat HaGolah, לשכת הגזית. Lishkat
HaGazit. Now we'll say what each one is for. לשכת העץ אמר
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב שכחתי מה היתה משמשת. Lishkat HaEtz, amar Rabi
Eliezer ben Yaakov, shakachti mah hayta meshameshet. So again, the fact that
he's always recorded as saying he forgot means that he was the
one that was providing most of the information, so he's assumed to
be the author of this מסכת. masechet. אבא שאול אומר לשכת כהן
גדול... Abba Shaul omer Lishkat Kohen Gadol... Yeah, he has a מסכת
masechet too, didn't he? Yes, yes, it was the לשכה lishka of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Now, okay, what does that mean? I
know that's where he would store his private stuff. Anyway, okay. Oh,
so actually, I'm sorry, the ראש Rosh says, the ראש Rosh says
that he's not answering רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
He's just, nobody, nobody's saying what it was used for. He's just
giving it a different name. It wasn't called the לשכת העץ, Lishkat
Ha'Etz, it was called the לשכת כהן גדול. Lishkat Kohen Gadol. We
don't have that on the diagram, do we? Do we have some
reference? Yeah, it's very actually quite funny that they don't include it
in this diagram. I don't know why. Okay, it's in other diagrams.
Okay. אחרי שתיהן, acharei shetehen, okay now, לשכת כהן גדול הייתה אחרי
שתיהן. Lishkat Kohen Gadol hayta acharei shetehen. Now this לשכה, lishka, which
nobody knew exactly what it was, was behind the other two לשכות,
lishkaot, which means to the south, to the west, and maybe also
like to the south of the other two. בגג שלושתן שווה, begag
sheloshtan shaveh, they all had the same roof. לשכת הגולה, Lishkat HaGolah,
what would they do there? שם היה בור קבוע, sham haya bor
kavua, there they had a fixed well. וגלגל נתון עליו, vegalgal natun
alav, and they had a, what do you call it, a wheel,
a whatever, what do you call those things? Anyway, not a wheel,
well it is a wheel, but pulley, thank you. ומשם מספיקין מים
לכל העזרה, umisham maspikin mayim lechol ha'azarah, that would be the way
they would get water into the עזרה. azarah. You need a lot
of water, right? You need to, first of all you get thirsty,
you need to rinse the floor. Where did you get your water?
So there was a well dug there in לשכת הגולה. Lishkat HaGolah.
Why is it called לשכת הגולה? Lishkat HaGolah? Some say it was
because the בני הגולה bnei hagolah dug it, maybe at one stage,
and some say because גולה golah like the word גל, gal, like
it was the word for the wheel. Okay, but that was how
they got water to the whole עזרה. azarah. לשכת הגזית, Lishkat HaGazit,
of the hewn stone, this is the one we all know about.
שם הייתה סנהדרין גדולה של ישראל יושבת, sham hayta Sanhedrin gedolah shel
Yisrael yoshevet, there the סנהדרין Sanhedrin would sit. Now of course you
can't sit in the עזרה, azarah, so they would sit in the
part that was towards the outside, towards, you know, towards and there
was a door towards the outside, so that had, did not have
קדושה, kedusha, so they were allowed to sit. ודנה את הכהונה, vedana
et hakehunah, now of course לשכת הגזית Lishkat HaGazit was the סנהדרין
הגדול, Sanhedrin HaGadol, they were like the Supreme Court, so you know,
eventually any case could come to them. But a major role they
played was to deal with questions that arose for the כוהנים, Kohanim,
in particular status issues of the כוהנים. Kohanim. And with this we
will end. כהן שנמצא בו פסול, Kohen shenimtza bo psul, לובש שחורים
ומתעטף שחורים. lovesh shachorim umit'atef shachorim. If they found, they investigated a
כהן Kohen and found that there was some פסול, psul, he was
a חלל, chalal, he was born from some forbidden union, then he
would have to dress in black clothes, wrap himself in a black
shawl, יוצא והולך לו, yotze veholech lo, and he would leave. ושלא
נמצא בו פסול, veshelo nimtza bo psul, and if somebody was being
investigated and then it was found that there was no invalidity, לובש
לבנים ומתעטף לבנים, lovesh levanim umit'atef levanim, he'd wear white and cloak
himself in white, נכנס ומשמש עם אחיו הכהנים, nichnas umeshamesh im echav
hakohanim, and then he would go and he would be able to
serve with his brothers the כוהנים. Kohanim. ויום טוב היו עושים, veyom
tov hayu osim, and they would make a party, they would make
a day of celebration, שלא נמצא פסול בזרעו של אהרן הכהן. shelo
nimtza psul bezaro shel Aharon hakohen. That they, that they, that there
was no invalidity now, except when they did, so some say it
means like if a whole day went by, and it's funny, like
how many days were they investigating them? But if a certain period
went by and nobody was, nobody had a problem, they would make
a party. וכך היו אומרים: vekach hayu omrim: ברוך המקום ברוך הוא
שלא נמצא פסול בזרעו של אהרן, Baruch hamakom baruch hu shelo nimtza
psul bezaro shel Aharon, וברוך הוא שבחר באהרן ובזרעו לעמוד ולשרת לפני
ה׳ בבית קדש הקדשים. ubaruch hu shebachar be'Aharon uvezaro la'amod ulesharit lifnei
Hashem beveit kodesh hakodashim. סליקא לך כל העזרה selika lach kol ha'azarah
וסליקא לך מסכת מידות uselika lach masechet middot וסליקא לך מסכת סדר
קדשים. veselika lach masechet seder kodashim. So שקויח shkoach to everybody. This
is the first סדר seder we've done together. We begin טהרות Taharos
and נידה Niddah tomorrow.